Guide to the Julia and Morris Mandelowitz World War II correspondence 2017.008
Brooklyn Historical Society
Julia and Morris Mandelowitz World War II correspondence
1930-2003
1942-1946
Center for Brooklyn History
2017.008
5 Linear Feet in 12 manuscript boxes.
This collection is comprised of thousands of WWII era letters, primarily between Morris and Julia (nee Emmer) Mandelowitz. The Brooklyn couple maintained a regular correspondence between 1941 and 1946, during which time Morris served as a gunnery instructor for the US Army. The bulk of the letters are primarily sent from the front to Brooklyn, but also include letters between friends, parents and other relatives. The letters offer insight into life in Brooklyn as well as on the front during WWII.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Marianne Erlichman and Alan Mandell, children of Julia and Morris Mandelowitz, 2017.
Appraisal
A small number of materials were removed from the collection during processing, including music books, Life magazines, and travel brochures.
Biographical / Historical
This collection is comprised of thousands of WWII era letters, primarily between Morris and Julia (nee Emmer) Mandelowitz. The Brooklyn couple maintained a regular correspondence between 1941 and 1946, during which time Morris served as a gunnery instructor for the US Army. The collection also includes many letters from friends and family serving in the war, or on the home front in Brooklyn. Both Julia and Morris's parents were European immigrants who lived in Brooklyn. Morris's parents, Charles and Rebecca Mandelowitz, owned a luncheonette in Brooklyn and later a hotel, Greenfield Manor, in the Catskills. Julia's parents, Andrew and Fanny Emmer, also lived in Brooklyn where her father worked as a milkman with a horse drawn carriage and her mother as a homemaker.
Morris and Julia married in 1943. At the end of the war, the couple returned to Brooklyn living in a converted garage on Rogers Avenue, and then to the Marine Park Co-ops on Burnett Street where they stayed for the remainder of their lives. They had two children, Alan Mandell and Marianne Erlichman. Julia was a bookkeeper at various companies in Brooklyn and Manhattan, and was also a homemaker. Morris worked for Metropolitan Life Insurance and Mack Truck, as well as other companies. Julia died on February 7th 2003, and Morris died December 26th 2004. The couple is buried together on Long Island.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of thousands of letters, primarily between Morris and Julia (Emmer) Mandelowitz. The bulk of the letters are between 1941 and 1946, primarily sent from the front to Brooklyn, but also include letters between friends, parents and other relatives. Friends and relatives were assigned all over the United States or world and many letters came from Julia's younger brother, Sammy, who was in the Merchant Marines and traveled from Europe, through the Panama Canal to the Pacific. The letters offer insight into life in Brooklyn as well as on the front during WWII. The correspondence documents day-to-day life, while also revealing the correspondents' hopes and aspirations for after the war. The correspondence is supplemented by army documents and family photographs.
Arrangement
Material is arranged in the order in which it was received from the donor.
Soldiers |z New York (State) |z New York |v Correspondence; United States -- Armed Forces -- World War, 1939-1945
- Correspondence, December 1933 to 1941 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, January 1941 to July 1943 (Box 2)
- Correspondence, August 1943 to January 1944 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, February 1944 to March 1944 (Box 4)
- Correspondence, April 1944 to August 1944 (Box 5)
- Correspondence, September 1944 to August 1944 (Box 6)
- Correspondence, February 1945 to April 1945 (Box 7)
- Correspondence, April 1945 to July 1945 (Box 8)
- Correspondence, August 1945 to January 1946 (Box 9)
- Correspondence, February 1946 to 1948 (Box 10)
- Military Documents (1), 1943 (Box 10)
- Military Documents (2), 1943 (Box 10)
- Military Documents (3), 1945-1946 (Box 10)
- Military Documents (4), circa 1940s (Box 10)
- Army Air Base Special Orders, January 1946 (Box 11)
- Army Air Forces Preflight School Course Books, circa 1940s (Box 11)
- Army Artifacts, circa 1940s (Box 11)
- Army Booklets, 1941-1943 (Box 11)
- Army Course Instruction Packet, 1943 (Box 11)
- Army Documents, circa 1940s (Box 11)
- Army Handbook of Servicing and Inspection, 1943 (Box 11)
- Army Lessons Plans, circa 1940s (Box 11)
- Army Preflight Classbooks, 1943 (Box 11)
- Army Soldier's Handbook, July 1941 (Box 11)
- Army War Department Manuals, March 1942 to April 1943 (Box 11)
- Assorted Family Douments (1), 1930-1979 (Box 11)
- Assorted Family Douments (2), circa 1940s (Box 11)
- Assorted Family Documents (3), circa 1940s (Box 11)
- Civil Aeronautics Bulletin Flight Fundamentals, February 1943 (Box 12)
- Electrical Circuits Notebook, 1941 (Box 12)
- Family Photos, 1940-2003 (Box 12)
- Judaism Booklets, 1943 (Box 12)
- Keesler Field News, November 1943 (Box 12)
- Morris Mandelowitz Notebook (1), 1944 (Box 12)
- Morris Mandelowitz Notebook (2), circa 1940s (Box 12)
- Morris Mandelowitz Yearbook and Diploma, 1937 (Box 12)
- Physics Notes, 1943 (Box 12)